Neal Carr

Location: Exeter, Devon

Email: neal.carr@metoffice.gov.uk

Profile

A software engineer at the Met Office, with a PhD in mathematical physics and a 2.1 degree in Mathematics from the University of Cambridge. Interested in applying strong mathematical problem-solving skills to practical, real-world problems. At the Met Office, I am currently developing programming experience to facilitate a career in software development.

Education and qualifications

University of Kent- 2014-2018: PhD in Mathematics: "The ODE/IM correspondence for simply-laced Lie algebras"

- My thesis was concerned with generalising the "ODE/IM correspondence" a connection between
 differential equations that generalise the Schrödinger equation, and mathematical descriptions of
 systems of many particles in two dimensions (an example of such system would be a model of
 ferromagnetism as seen in everyday magnets.)
- Used Mathematica to facilitate laborious calculations and test new mathematical ideas. Also used
 Python to write more portable code and solve systems of complex non-linear equations. Developed
 project management and research skills. Gave talks about my research to other PhD students and the
 local research group (South East Mathematical Physics Seminar)

King's College London- 2013-2014: MSc in Theoretical Physics – Distinction

Continued to pursue my interest in Theoretical Physics. Completed a short dissertation in the summer
of 2014, summarising the results of a research paper and demonstrating understanding of its main
results. Dissertation received award for best project of the year.

University of Cambridge- 2009-2012: BA in Mathematics - 2.i

- Attended a wide variety of courses with a particular focus on Applied Mathematics and Theoretical Physics. Developed problem-solving,
- Completed coursework using MATLAB.

De Lisle College- 2002-2009:

• A-Levels: A in Maths, Further Maths, Physics and Chemistry. 11 GCSEs A*-A, including Maths and English.

Work experience

September 2019 – present: Met Office

Foundation Scientific Software Engineer

• I assist with maintenance and updating of the UKCA (United Kingdom Chemistry and Aerosols) component of the Unified Model. I work closely with scientist colleagues to assist them to implement new functionality, bugfixes, and improvements to the model.

 Also working to prepare UKCA for its incorporation into LFRic, the Met Office's new climate/weather model designed for modern supercomputers.

November 2018 – January 2019: Advanced Geochemical Systems

Mathematical Modeller

- Worked on a short project modelling temperature distribution of region of Earth's crust to aid in location of potential hydrocarbon deposits.
- Constructed mathematical model using Python. Output data sets were presented to client in clear format, and model was fine-tuned using feedback from client.

September 2014 – September 2018 University of Kent

Tutorial Leader

 Led several tutorials for undergraduates. Responsible for guiding the students through their assigned problem sets. Consistently received good feedback for my teaching through the university's anonymous feedback system.

September 2012 – September 2013: Blue Tutors

Tier 1 Tutor

• Gained additional one-to-one teaching experience working as a part-time tutor.

Additional experience

- Took part in a week-long modelling camp at the University of Edinburgh, collaborating with a team of other PhD students on a practical engineering problem.
- Ran the Assassins' Guild May Week game at Cambridge. Updated the website displaying the status of the game (using basic HTML) and mediated disputes between players.
- Assisted in the running of a "Code Club" at a local primary school, helping children to learn how to code- first with Scratch, a simplified visual programming language, and then with Python.
- Some hobbyist experience with C/C++.

Kev skills

Python, FORTRAN, Mathematica, C/C++, research, communication (giving talks, teaching), Full UK driving licence